Guide to the Ralph Adimari Papers 1931-1970 (Bulk 1957-1963) MSS 28A MSS 028A
© 2012 Fales Library and Special Collections
Ralph Adimari Papers
1931-1970 (Bulk 1957-1964)
MSS 028A
© 2012 Fales Library and Special Collections
1.0 linear feet (3 boxes)
Ralph T. Adimari (1902-1970) was an editor, researcher, and historian of the dime novel, a class of popular fiction that thrived in the mid to late nineteenth century and into the early twentieth. The Ralph Adimari Papers contain records of Adimari's research, including correspondence, notebooks, clippings, photographs, and ephemera.
Provenance
Ralph Adimari sold parts of his collection of dime novels and research material, including the William J. Benners Papers, to Edward G. Levy beginning in 1964. Levy, the dime novel collector and historian, donated the Ralph Adimari Papers to Fales in 1965-1966.
Access Restrictions
Open to researchers. Appointments are necessary to consult archive and manuscript materials.
Biographical Note
Ralph T. Adimari (1902-1970) was an editor, researcher, and historian of the dime novel, a class of popular fiction that thrived in the mid to late nineteenth century and into the twentieth. The term "dime novels" refers to inexpensive, cheaply produced paperbacks and serials, often romance, adventure, westerns, or detective stories. A prodigious collector, Adimari did extensive research on dime novels, and published many articles in Dime Novel Round-Up before 1940, and at least 20 articles between 1954 and 1964. He also wrote a piece titled "Saga of a Dime Novelist" which appeared in American Book Collector in early 1935. Through correspondence with fellow dime novel historian and DNRU editor Ralph F. Cummings, Adimari acquired the letters and notebooks of William J. Benners (1863-1940), a dime novel historian, author, and agent, and wrote a biography of Benners for the DNRU. Building upon Benners's work identifying dime novel authors, Adimari compiled detailed lists of authors and pseudonyms, titles, and publishers, definitively solving several mysteries about dime novel authorship.
Adimari was born Raphael Adimare on October 19, 1902. He lived in the New York City area for most of his life, including Mount Vernon and Suffolk. In addition to his work on dime novels, he co-edited a 1936 collection of Walt Whitman's essays, titled New York Dissected. Adimari died November 1970 in Suffolk, New York.
Scope and Content Note
The Ralph Adimari Papers contain correspondence from fellow dime novel collectors and historians, including Edward G. Levy, Dr. Albert Johannsen, Dime Novel Round-Up editors Edward T. LeBlanc and Ralph Cummings, the latter from whom Adimari acquired William Benners's papers, and writers including Col. Charles D. Randolph, aka "Buckskin Bill," known for his dime-novel and Western themed poetry. Also included are notebooks of research, manuscripts, newspaper clippings related to dime novel authors, photographs, and Victoriana. The William J. Benners Papers, also housed in Fales, includes several of Benners's notebooks that were subsequently used and annotated by Adimari.
Arrangement
Series IA consists of correspondence. Material is arranged into folders alphabetically by correspondent; within each folder the letters are arranged chronologically. Series IB consists of notebooks, manuscripts, clippings, photographs, and other miscellany.
Series I A: Correspondence, 1931-1970
Series I B: Notebooks, Loose Notes, Lists, Manuscripts, Photos, Victoriana, Printed Materials
Related Material at Fales Library and Special Collections
Levy Dime Novel Collection
William J. Benners Papers
Separated Material
There is no information about materials that are associated by provenance to the described materials that have been physically separated or removed.
Benners, William J., (William James), 1863-1940; Cummings, Ralph F., 1898-; Johannsen, Albert, 1871-1962; LeBlanc, Edward T.; Leithead, J. Edward.; Levy, Edward G.; Randolph, Charles D; Adventure stories, American.; American fiction |y 19th century.; American fiction |y 20th century.; Clippings (information artifacts); Dime novels.; Manuscripts for publication.; Notebooks.; Personal correspondence.; Personal papers.; Photographs.; Popular literature |z United States.; Victoriana.; Visiting cards.
- Series I A: Correspondence, 1931-1970.
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence to and from individuals, including authors, relating to Adimari's dime novel research.
  - Cummings, Ralph G., 1957-1963 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    Includes 1962 letter from Cummings on Benners's stationary.
  - Guinon, J.P., 1961-1963 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Johannsen, Albert, 1950-1962 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - LeBlanc, Edward T., 1956-1963 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Leithead, J. Edward, 1958-1963 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Levy, Edward G., 1964-1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Includes letters from Adimari to Levy and biographical information about Levy.
  - Randolph, Charles D. aka "Buckskin Bill", 1962 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Van Devier, Roy B., 1955-1961 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Willson, Frank C., 1958-1960 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous, 1931-1961 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series I B: Notebooks, loose notes, lists, manuscripts, photos, Victoriana, printed material.
  Extensive notes on the history of dime novels; lists of dime novel titles, authors, pseudonyms, and publishers; printed material and other ephemera related to Adimari's research; Adimari's biography of William J. Benners in Dime Novel Round-up.
  - N otes, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    A collection of loose notes on Dime Novel authors.
  - Notebook, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Marble composition book "I" contains bibliographical lists and notes on various publications.
  - Notes, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    A collection of notes transcribed "from the William James Benners Jr. collection owned by Ralph F. Cummings."
  - Notebook, "Cushing -- Pseudonyms + More Notes", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Composition book contains notes on William Cushing's Initials and Pseudonyms: A Dictionary of Literary Disguises.
  - Notebook, "Dime Novel Notes", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Memorandum book contains notes on Dime Novels and authors, arranged alphabetically.
  - Notebook, "Literary Notes + Alger Notes", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Notebook contains author and pseudonym lists, notes by William Benners, and other research.
  - Notebook and loose notes (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Marble composition book "II" contains notes on various publications, especially the New York Dramatic Mirror and notes labeled "Miscellaneous." Two newspaper clippings are pasted in the book. Loose pages include notes on the Mirror"continued from composition book," various publication checklists, and other research.
  - Non-Dime Novel Notes (Box 2, Folder 8)
    A collection of loose notes.
  - Notebook, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 9A)
    "Penmark" marble composition book labeled "Ledger Serials" contains miscellaneous notes on serials and authors.
  - Notebook, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 9B)
    "Giant" composition book contains notes on various publications.
  - Notebook, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 9C)
    "Penmark" marble composition book labeled "Book Reviews."
  - Loose notes, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 10A)
    A collection of notes labeled "Dime Novel Notes + Boys' Serials."
  - Notebook, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 10B)
    Memo book labeled "First Notes" on one cover, and "Miscellaneous" on the other.
  - Notebook, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 10C)
    Memo book labeled "Miscellany / Not Dime Novel" contains miscellaneous notes.
  - Manuscripts, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Photographs, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Victoriana, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Calling cards, Christmas cards, etc.
  - Notes, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Miscellaneous notes, some on legal-size paper.
  - Lists, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Type- and handwritten lists of: William Benners's correspondents; Benners's works; publications; pseudonym identifications.
  - Newspaper clippings, 1922-1962 (Box 3, Folder 3A)
    Photocopies of newspaper clippings re: authors A-K, including Benners.
  - Newspaper clippings, 1926-1962 (Box 3, Folder 3B)
    Photocopies of newspaper clippings re: authors L-Z.
  - Newspaper clippings, 1963, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Newspaper clippings, including lists of the Pinkerton Detective Series (Laird and Lee), Ten- and Twenty-Cent Novelettes, Threepenny Novels, and Beadle's Dime Library.
  - Printed materials, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Three pieces of printed material: (1) flyer for upcoming serials in National Farmer and Home Magazine; (2) flyer for Mrs. George Sheldon Downs' "Love and Beauty, or, the Heiress of Dunleigh," published by William Benners for his Constance Library imprint, including blurbs by Benners; (3) folder for Dime Novel Club facsimile reprint no. 6A, 1945.
  - Printed material: Dime Novel Round-Up, Vol. 26, No. 9, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Features Adimari's biography of William J. Benners.